In this assignment we will setup the camera
本任务中我们会设定相机
and lighting for our game.
和光线
Our game will be a top-down style game
我们的游戏是俯视类型的游戏
where we are looking down on the game area
我们从固定的位置
from a fixed position above the game.
自上方向下看整个游戏区域
If we switch to the Game view we can see
当我们调整一下游戏的视窗的角度
that the camera is in a completely different
我们发现摄像机的位置完全不在
position from where it needs to be for our game
它应该在的地方
When we look at the main camera in the Scene view
从Scene视图上来看，相机的位置在
we can see that it is behind the player
玩家飞船对象的后方
game object and slightly above it.
略微高于游戏玩家对象一点点
This is the default starting position for the
这个位置是每个新视图的
main camera in a new scene.
相机的默认位置
Unity will always include a default main
Unity 总会为新的场景
camera at this position in every new scene.
在这个位置设置一个相机
At this point it's worth noting that in the
我们还需要了解
Scene view, when we have a camera selected
在Scene视图中，当我们点选了相机
we can see a preview for that camera in the
我们可以在Scene视图右下角看到
lower right of the Scene view.
这个相机的预览效果
So we want to move the camera to
我们想把相机的位置
a position above the game area
移动到游戏区域的顶端
where it is looking down on the game.
并且从上向下看这个游戏
Don't forget that the camera is simply a
不要忘记,这里的相机
camera component attached to a game
只是一个在场景的游戏对象
object in our scene.
它的上面附着了相机的组件
We can manipulate the camera in our scene
我们可以通过改变相机的变形组件
by effecting the camera's transform.
来控制相机
First let's reset the camera's transform
首先让我们来重置下相机的变形组件
by using Reset on the context sensitive gear menu.
点击Transform组件右上角的齿轮下拉菜单中的Reset
This will reset the transform values and
变形组件中的值将被重置
set the camera to the origin point with
相机将会被放置在原点
no rotation and a scale of 1.
没有旋转,缩放也被置为1
With the camera at origin let's rotate it
我们先将相机旋转一下
to face down by adjusting the rotation
使相机视角变成从上而下
on the X axis to 90 degrees.
调整旋转将其沿X轴旋转90度
Next let's grab the transform
然后我们我们抓住这个箭头来
by using the transform handles
改变变形组件的值
and lift it up along the Y axis.
抓着它沿Y轴上移
We can see how the camera preview is updating
我们可以看到随着相机位置的变化
to show what the camera is rendering
预览图的内容也在逐步变化
For our game we can simply change
对我们的游戏而言
the Y value to 10,
我们只需把Y值设定为10
placing the camera 10 units above the player ship.
把相机放到玩家飞船上方10个单位处
Now that the camera is in place, let's setup
现在相机的位置设置好了,下一步设置
the camera component.
相机的组件
The first decision we need to make is about
首先要决定的是相机的
the camera type.
类型
Will our projection be perspective or orthographic?
我们的投影是透视还是正交?
Our game needs to feel like an upright arcade game.
我们的游戏追求一种自上而下的街机的感觉
These did not have any perspective
这里面不需要透视
(物体有近大远小)
so we will choose orthographic as our projection mode.
所以我们选择正交(物体不受近大远小影响)作为我们的投影模式
When we are using a perspective camera
当我们使用投影相机的时候
if we want to change how much of our game
如果我们想改变
the camera sees we can adjust the
相机可见部分的大小
field of view value.
我们可以通过改变field of view的值来实现
This is a lot like changing the zoom on a
这个操作有点像操作
real world camera.
真实相机的缩放功能
The larger the field of view, the wider
更大的field of view的值意味着
the lens as it were,
更广的视野
and the more our camera can see and render.
我们可以看到更多物体，同时计算机也需要做更多的渲染
When we are using an orthographic camera
当我们使用正交相机的时候
we can adjust how much the camera will see
我们可以通过改变正交尺寸的大小
by changing the orthographic size.
改变相机的视野大小
But what is the correct size for our game?
但是什么样的视野尺寸是适合我们的游戏的呢?
We can see a fairly reasonable representation
我们可以在预览窗口看到
of the camera in the preview window.
相机的视野的情况
But it might be better to do any final
但是如果可以在最终的游戏视图上
adjustments in the Game view itself.
调整那样就更好了
We will still have control over the component
我们仍然可以通过Inspector 标签
in the Inspector and we can see the
下的组建进行控制同时我们也可以看到
actual camera output full size.
全尺寸的相机真实输出。
It seems that the ship feels right when the
当正交的尺寸在10左右的时候
orthographic size is around 10.
飞船的大小刚刚好
So let's set that value to around 10 exactly.
所以让我们把这个值设置为10
Now the player is in the exact centre of the game area.
现在玩家飞船在游戏区域的正中央.
I feel that the ship should start
我觉得,飞船在开始的时候
near the bottom of the screen.
位置应该在屏幕的底部
What's the best way to do this?
有什么好方法呢?
We could switch back in to the Scene view
我们先切换回场景视图
and move the ship by dragging the ship's
通过移动飞船的变形手柄来改变
transform handles, but we have no good feedback
飞船的位置,但是我们没法从
from the Game view or the camera to know if
游戏视图或者相机视野得知
we have chosen the correct position.
我们的移动到的位置是否是正确的
We could change our layout so we have both
我们可以改变一下我们的视窗布局
the Game and the Scene view open at the same time.
让游戏视图和场景视图同时打开
But we don't need to.
其实我们并不需要这么做
Let's switch back to the Game view
让我切换回游戏视图
and move the ship while we are able to see it
我们可以在全尺寸游戏视图中
in the full sized Game view window.
移动飞船
We will need to move the ship by directly
我们需要通过直接改变飞船的变形组建
manipulating the ship's transform component.
来移动飞船
We want to move the ship along the Z axis,
我们需要将飞船沿着Z轴移动
so click on the Field title,
所以点击下这个输入栏左侧标题的位置
in this case the Z,
这里我们点击字母Z
and drag back and forth until the ship
然后我们来回拖拽鼠标
looks correct in the scene.
直到找到飞船在场景中的合适位置
Now we have a problem.
这里产生一个问题
We really want the player's game object
如果我们的需要玩家对象
to be at origin.
所在的位置是原点的话...
We want this for 2 reasons.
这里面有2个原因
1, it just feels better to me.
1,我喜欢这么干
And 2, it will make certain steps
2,这么做会让后续的核心步骤
later on in this project easier to manage.
处理起来更容易一些.
Yet I still want to have the player's ship
但我仍然希望玩家飞船从
start down here at the bottom of the game area.
游戏区域的下方开始
Well as we know, all things are relative.
我们知道,所有的都是相对的
So let's move the camera, not the player.
因此,我们移动相机的位置,不移动玩家的位置.
Reset the ship's transform back to origin
将玩家飞船的变形组件重置,使飞船回到原点
and select the main camera.
选择主相机
Again, by dragging the Field title,
再拖拽一次输入框的标题
move the camera's transform up along the Z axis
将相机的沿Z轴做变换
until the ship is in a good position.
直到飞船的位置符合我们的需要
This feels like a good position for the player's ship.
目前玩家飞船的位置刚刚好
Let's clean up the value for the camera's
我们调整一下相机的值
transform Z axis.
变换组件Z轴
A clean round 5 is good.
这个值为大约为5
Next let's set the camera's background.
下一步,我们要设定相机的背景
Currently we have the default background
目前是系统默认的背景
found in the Clear Flag setting.
这个是根据Clear Flag设置的
This is Skybox.
现在选定的是Skybox
We won't be using a skybox today,
我们今天将不再使用skybox
we simply want a black background.
我们只想要一个黑色的背景.
So let's change the clear flags
我们改一下clear flags
to solid colour.
改为solid colour(纯色)
It's worth noting that if our clear flags
值得注意的是,如果我们将clear flags
is set to Skybox and we have no
设定为Skybox但是有没配置skybox
skybox assigned clear flags will use the
clear flags将会使用
background colour instead.
背景颜色替代
This is why, even though we have skybox selected,
这就是我们选择了skybox但是我们看到的仍然是
we see the blue from the background colour.
蓝色的背景颜色的原因.
Click on the colour box.
点击颜色框
This will bring up a colour picker.
会出现一个颜色选择器.
Let's make our background black.
我们将我们的背景颜色设置成黑色.
When we are done we can close the colour picker.
选择完成后关闭颜色选择器.
We have no lights in this scene.
我们的场景目前没有光
Our background is black, yet we can still
我们的背景也是黑色的,即使这样我们仍然能看到
see our player ship. Why is that?
我们的玩家飞船.这是为什么?
If we go to Edit - Render Settings
我们点选菜单Edit - Render Settings
we can see a property called Ambient Light.
我们看到有一个属性叫做Ambient Light(环境光)
Ambient Light is the light from
Ambient Light不是从固定点光源
no fixed point that lights all
发出的,它会照亮场景中
the surfaces in the scene.
所有的表面.
All new scenes have an ambient light set to
所有的新场景的环境光的值都被设定为
(51, 51, 51).
(51, 51, 51)
So every new scene has a very
所以说每个新的场景都有非常微弱的
dim ambient light added to all objects in that scene.
环境光照射在该场景的全部物体上
These values can be adjusted to add
这个值可以被改为增加单色光
a general colour or full white light
或者增加完全亮度的白光
to all objects in the scene.
覆盖场景中的全部物体
However, this light has no directionality
然而,这个光是无方向的
and it can be very unflattering if used incorrectly.
如果使用不当就会变得很麻烦
We will set our ambient light to Black,
我们将环境光设定为黑色
effectively turning it off.
实际上就是关掉了环境光
Now let's light our scene.
现在让我们自行设置我们场景中的光
We will be creating a modified 3 point lighting
我们会为游戏建立一个改进的3点照明系统
system for our game with a main or key light,
其中一点是主光源或核心光源
a fill light and a rim light.
一个补光光源和一个轮廓光光源
These three lights will show off the shapes of
这个三点照明将会展示出我们物体的外形
our objects and give our game a
给我们的游戏场景烘托
good sense of atmosphere.
很好的氛围
Start by selecting Create - Directional Light
现在开始在Hierarchy视窗中点击Create - Directional Light
from the Create menu in the Hierarchy view.
Create - Directional Light
This will add a directional light to our scene
这个操作会在我们场景中增加一个定向的光源
Rename this game object Main Light.
将这个对象改名为Main Light
Next let's reset the light's position.
下一步,重置光源的位置.
This will set the light to origin.
这个步骤会将光源设置到原点
We won't see any change in the lighting
整个场景的光照似乎没什么变化
as directional lights light the entire scene
因为定向光源会照亮整个场景
based on their rotation, not their position.
只与光照角度有关,与光源位置无关
Switching back to the Scene view will show us the light
切换回场景试图,上面显示了光，
and the gizmo will show us it's
小图标显示了
orientation in the scene.
光在场景中的方向
Let's now reset the rotation as well,
现在我们把旋转的值也重置一下
so we can have a clean set of values to start from.
这样便于我们重新设置初始值
This is our main light, so it will be the
现在设置的这个是主光源,所以是最亮的
brightest and most important.
也是最重要的光源
We need to see the light on the ship
我们希望从玩家上方的主相机中看到
from our main camera, which is above the player.
光照亮飞船
So let's tilt the main light down on to
因此，让我们将主光源倾斜一下
the scene, but not too much.
但是不要倾斜的太多
We want to see the shape of the ship,
我们想看到飞船的形状
but not wash it out.
但是不要太亮
That looks good. It's nearly at 20 degrees.
现在刚刚好.大约20度
So let's clean up that value to around
所以我们将X这个值设定为
20 degrees down in to the scene.
与场景成20度角
Now let's rotate the light around on it's Y axis
现在让我再沿Y轴旋转一下光
and bring the light in from the side.
让光线从侧面照过来
Let's pick a good point towards the front
我们找一个从前方照过来的方向
but not directly in front.
但是不要正前方
It feels good about here.
目前的位置刚刚好
Let's clean up these values to around -115.
这里我们将Y值设定为-115.
To see how this light works in our game
我们切换回游戏视图
let's switch back to the Game view.
看看这个光线效果如何
We want the main light to feel like the light
我们想让主光看起来像是
from a nearby sun, so let's increase the
从附近的太阳照过来的，所以增加光的
intensity to 0.75.
强度到0.75.
This gives a nice hot feeling to
现在给人一种
the right side of the ship.
飞船的右侧很热的感觉
We could change the colour, but let's
我们可以改变光的颜色
leave the main light at white for now.
这里我们暂时还是先使用白光
This lighting might seem realistic for some
这个光线给人一种空间很广很深的真实感
deep space environment but the other side
但是飞船的另一侧
of the ship is far too dark for this game.
在游戏场景中表现的太暗了
To light this side of the ship we need another light.
为了照亮这一侧，我们需要另一个光.
This will be our fill light, to fill in the
这个就是我们的补光,补光的作用是
shadows on the far side.
让我们看清阴影中的部分
To build our fill light duplicate the main light.
我们复制下主光源作为补光
Make sure the main light is selected
先选定主光源
and then use Edit - Duplicate
然后点选Edit - Duplicate
or use the hot-key combination.
或者使用热键组合
Rename the duplicate Fill Light.
将复制出来的对象改名Fill Light(补光).
These 2 lights are now doubling up on the same
这两个光现在叠加照在了
surfaces as the lights add together.
同一个面上
Don't worry, we'll soon change this.
别急,我们现在就改过来
First, let's reset the rotation on the fill light
首先,将补光的旋转重置一下
and then switch to the Scene view so we can see
再切换到场景视图便于观察
the gizmo on the light.
光线方向的那个小图标.
We could set this light by eye in the Game view
我们可以直接在游戏视图中肉眼设定这个光
but it can also be helpful to see the light's
但是通过这个光线的小图标来
gizmo when making adjustments.
做微调也十分有用
Let's grab the fill light and rotate it around
我们抓住补光让它沿Y轴
on the Y axis.
旋转
Here we want to light the other side of the ship.
我们想让补光照到飞船的另一边
Also from a direction in front of the ship
仍然要从靠前的方向照过来
to compliment the key light.
来配合我们的主光源
This feels good.
这个感觉刚好
Let's look at the lighting in the Game view.
让我们看下游戏视图光线的感觉
The direction of the fill light looks good
补光的方向看起来可以了
but it's feeling like we now have 2 main lights.
但是现在看起来像是2个主光的样子
We don't need 2 main lights,
我们不需要2个主光
so let's reduce the intensity of the fill light
所以我们把补光的强度减弱一些
down to 0.5.
减小到0.5.
And let's change the colour as well
同时我们改一下光的颜色
A hint of blue will tell us that this is a secondary light.
偏一点蓝色暗示这个光是一个次等光
Let's reduce the red channel to 128
我们将红色通道的强度减小到128
and then let's also reduce the values of
我们将绿色和蓝色通道的
the green and blue channels as well,
值也减小
down to about 192.
到192
Generally darkening our fill colour.
总体上让我们的补光颜色更暗一些
By toggling the fill light we can see how it's
我们可以通过打开关闭补光的开关
lighting that side of the ship.
来观察飞船另一侧的补光效果
Lastly, let's tilt down a little in to the scene,
最后我们把光线稍微倾斜一些
5 degrees is enough,
5度就够了
and let's clean up the rotation on the Y axis,
我们将沿Y轴旋转的数据
making it a nice round 125. That looks good.
设定在125.看起来还不错.
Now let's add the rim light.
再让我们添加最后的边缘光
Duplicate the fill light and rename it Rim Light.
复制下补光然后重名名为边缘光
So we can see our rim light,
现在我们可以看到我们的边缘光
which will be fairly subtle,
这光看起来有点奇怪
let's turn off the fill light.
我们先关闭补光
Now select the rim light and reset the
选定边缘光然后
transform to remove the rotational values.
重置下变形的参数来消除旋转的值
This rim light needs to be fairly clear
边缘光需要足够的清楚
and it needs to stand out when mixing in
要能够清楚地与补光区分开来
with the fill light, so let's change the
所以将颜色改为
colour to pure white.
纯白色
Now we want to light the rear of the ship
我们想照亮穿的尾部
in a way that compliments the fill light.
这样可以更好的配合补光
So let's rotate the light around to catch
我们旋转光线
the rear edges of the ship,
让它刚好照到尾部的边缘
but on the same side as the fill.
它要与补光在同一侧
This looks good.
这个位置刚好
Let's make this value a clean 65 degrees.
我们将这个Y值设定在65度
This shows the edge well, but it's also
现在边缘清楚了,
acting now like a second fill light.
但是这个看起来像是另一个补光
This is mostly due to how much light
这是因为有些光照到了
spills on to the top of the ship.
船的顶部
To fix this let's rotate the light on the X axis
我们可以通过把光线沿X轴旋转来解决这个问题
and come up from below.
让光线从下往上照
Now this may seem counter intuitive,
这么看似乎违反直觉
as we are looking down on the ship,
好像我们在看穿底部似的
but this will keep the light from shining on the top
但是这么做会让光线照到边缘
surface of the ship and it will still
同时并不会照射到
catch the edges that we need to light.
飞船的上表面
-15 degrees seems fine.
-15度似乎刚好
Lastly, let's drop the intensity down to 0.25.
我们最后还需要把光强度降低到0.25
This may seem overly subtle
这个看起来不怎么自然
but when we add the fill light back in
但是当我们把补光重新打开的时候
we can see that they add together to give
补光和边缘光配合
us a good rim light and fill.
起来给我们非常好的感觉
Now that we have added our lights to the hierarchy
我们在层级视窗中添加了光
they are sorted alphabetically and mixed in
它们和其他的游戏物体
with all of the other game objects.
按照字母顺序混合排在了一起
This is not very well organised.
这个组织结构看起来有点乱
If we look in to our Scene view and select our new lights
如果我们从场景视图看我们新加的光线
the gizmos appear right where we are working
小图标会在场景的正中央
on top of our ship in the middle of the scene.
的飞船上显示出来
Let's add some organisation to our scene.
我们重新组织一下我们的场景
We can organise our scene by using empty game object.
我们可以通过新建空对象的方式来归类我们的对象
Add a new empty game object to the scene using the hot-key.
使用热键增加一个新的空的游戏对象
Use shift-command-N on the mac
苹果电脑上使用shift-command-N
and shift-control-N on windows.
windows电脑上使用shift-control-N on windows
Rename this Lighting.
重命名这个空对象为Lighting
Reset the game object's transform.
重置改对象的变形参数值
It's important to note this step
这步很重要
When we are using empty game objects
我们新建了一个空的游戏对象
to organise our hierarchy
来管理我们的层级视图
those game objects should be at origin
这些空的游戏对象应该在坐标原点
with no rotation and a scale of 1.
没有旋转并且尺寸大小是1
This can be accomplished by simply
这个操作可以由
resetting the transform component.
重置变形插件来完成
Now that we have setup our lighting game object
现在光照游戏对象已经建好了
we can drag our lights in to it.
把我们的光拖拽进去
This organises our hierarchy and keeps
这样我们的层级结构看起来更清晰
our lights together.
我们的光也都被放置到了一起
To clean up the gizmos at origin
如果我们不想看到光线的这些小图标
we can move our lighting parent game object
我们只需要把光照对象这个父类
up on the Y axis to get it out of the way.
沿Y轴上移将它们移出视线
Let's move them up by 100 units.
我们上移100个单位
Now, there they are, up there out of the way.
现在这些小图标已经被上移不再碍眼了
We can move these lights like this because
我们可以这样移动这些光
they are directional lights
因为他们是方向性光源
and directional lights light the entire scene
方向性光源照射进设图
based on their transform's rotation
只与变形的旋转有关
not their position.
与光本身的位置无关
This sets up our camera and our lighting.
我们的相机和光照配置好了
In the next assignment we will create
下一章节,我们将会
a background for our game.
配置游戏背景